Henry Russel Lectureship Committee (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Russel Lectureship Committee (University of Michigan) records 1925-2005
University of Michigan. Henry Russel Lectureship Committee.
8724 Bimu C8 1
University of Michigan committee which selects the annual Henry Russell Lecturer, the highest faculty award and the nominee for the Henry Russell Award recognizing a junior faculty member for superior scholarship and teaching ability.
2 linear feet in 2.4 boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Henry Russel Lectureship Committee (Accession No. 6536 ) makes periodic additions to the record group. Records first received in 1990.
The record group is open for research.
The Henry Russel Lectureship Committee of the University of Michigan is charged with nominating a distinguished university faculty member to deliver the annual Henry Russel Lecture, the highest award the university bestows on a member of its faculty. The committee also nominates a junior faculty member for the Henry Russel Award for distinguished scholarship and teaching ability.
The Board of Regents of the University of Michigan created the Henry Russel Lectureship on 25 May 1925. They authorized the giving of a special lecture by a distinguished member of the university faculty who would be known as the Henry Russel Lecturer. The Board of Regents also authorized the appointment of a junior member of the faculty as the recipient of the Henry Russel Award in the same action.
Henry Russel, three-time graduate of the University of Michigan (A.B. 1873; LL.B. 1875; A.M. 1876), was a prominent Detroit lawyer for many years. Upon his death in 1920, Russel bequeathed to the University of Michigan $10,000 for an endowment fund, "the income of which was to be used only to pay additional compensation to members of the instructing staff of the University." (Russel will) The Board of Regents of the University of Michigan created the Lectureship and Award in his honor through this fund
The Henry Russel Lectureship has been awarded annually since 1925 to an active senior member of the faculty, selected for distinguished achievement in research and instruction. The Russel Lecturer nomination is presented to the Regents of the University of Michigan by the Henry Russel Lectureship Committee, consisting of former Russel Lecturers and the Council of the Research Club. The Lectureship Committee nominates the most distinguished candidate for the Russel Lecturer from letters of recommendation sent from each nominee's peer group of study from the university and internationally within an academic year. There is a stipend associated with the Russel Lectureship which is provided by the bequest from Henry Russel.
The records of the Henry Russel Lectureship committee are arranged in four record series:
General Files
Nomination Files
Photographs
Audio Cassettes
The Henry Russel Lectureship Committee record group provides for unique research possibilities. An overview of the history of teaching at the University of Michigan can be examined throughout these files, primarily documenting the period from 1969 to 1989. The collection is arranged into four record series: General Files, Nomination Files, Photographs, and Audio Cassettes.
Subjects:
Henry Russel Award (University of Michigan); Russel, Henry, 1852-1920.; University of Michigan. Henry Russel Lectureship Committee.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Henry Russel Award (University of Michigan); Russel, Henry, 1852-1920.; University of Michigan. Henry Russel Lectureship Committee.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Agranoff, Bernard W., 1926-; Bassett, Leslie, 1923-; Coon, Minor Jesser, 1921-; Donahue, Thomas M.; Fine, Sidney, 1920-; Fulton, William, 1939-; Henry Russel Award (University of Michigan); Kish, George, 1914-1989; Matthews, Rowena G.; Mouron, Gérard A.; Vinovskis, Maris.; University of Michigan. Henry Russel Lectureship Committee.
Genre/Form:
Sound recordings.; Photographs.; CD-ROMs.
- History
  The History series includes a brief biography of Henry Russel in various draft forms by a past Henry Russel Lecturer, Dr. Edward H. Kraus. A short biographical sketch of Dr. Kraus is in the same folder (the Edward H. Kraus papers contain further information).
  - History of Henry Russel Lecturers (Box 1)
  - Biography of Henry Russel (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series includes minutes, correspondence, publicity, and lists. The scattered minutes of the Henry Russel Lectureship Committee cover the years from 1971 to 1985. Correspondence files of the Henry Russel Lectureship Committee, spanning the years 1955 to 1989, document changes in the operation of the functions of the organization. In 1970, there was an increase in the stipend provided for subsequent lecturers and award winners. In 1973, the taxation regulations for such awards changed, affecting the Lectureship to a degree, which is described in one folder in the collection. The correspondence files also contain nominations as well as order of exercises for the award ceremony for some years. Also included is material documenting the 1986 Henry Russel Lectureship Research Committee plans for reorganization. The publicity files include documentation of the effort to promote the Henry Russel Lectureship's prestige and coverage outside the University of Michigan's community through newspaper articles and press releases.
  - Correspondence 1955-1990, 5 folders (Box 1)
    (includes nominations and order of exercises)
  - Lectureship lists 1925-1988 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1971-1985 (Box 1)
  - Publicity 1955-1983 (Box 1)
  - Research Committee reorganization 1986 (Box 1)
- Nomination Files
  The series, Nomination Files, contains names and background material of past nominees and recipients of the Henry Russel Lectureship. These files are arranged chronologically and cover the years from 1973 to 1994 and 1999. These dates represent the year in which the nomination was made, but may also include nominations carried over from previous years. Information about persons who were nominated in more than one year is found in a file for the most recent year in which they were nominated. Some letters of recommendations are included. The series also includes the names and background material, including letters of recommendation, for the nominees and recipients of the Henry Russel Award. These files are also arranged chronologically and cover the years 1991 to 1999.
  - Henry Russel Lecture
    - 1973
      - William L. Root (Box 1)
    - 1975
      - Robert E. Moyers (Box 1)
    - 1976
      - Charles Gibson (Box 1)
    - 1977
      - Stefan S. Fajans (Box 1)
    - 1978
      - Avedis Donabedian 1974, 1977, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Bernard W. Agranoff (Box 1)
    - 1979
      - Halvor Niels Chrstensen (Box 1)
    - 1980
      - Emmett N. Leith (Box 1)
    - 1981
      - Leslie Kish (Box 1)
      - J. David Singer (Box 1)
    - 1982
      - Leslie Bassett (Box 1)
    - 1984
      - Philip Converse (Box 1)
      - Sidney Fine (Box 1)
      - Charles G. Overberger (Box 1)
      - Thomas M. Donahue 1984, 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985
      - Kamal Asgar (Box 1)
      - Warren H. Wagner, Jr. (Box 1)
    - 1987
      - Bernard W. Agranoff (Box 1)
      - Richard D. Alexander (Box 1)
    - 1989
      - Robert Axelrod (Box 1)
      - Bob Craig (Box 1)
    - 1990
      - Ross Chambers (Box 1)
      - Frederick Gehring (Box 1)
      - Yale Kasimir (Box 1)
      - Frederick Neidhardt (Box 1)
    - 1991
      - Minor J. Coon (Box 1)
    - 1992
      - John Holland (Box 1)
      - Elizabeth Douvan (Box 1)
    - 1994
      - William Bolcom (Box 1)
      - Ludwig Koenen (Box 1)
      - Vincent Massey (Box 1)
    - 1999 (Box 3)
  - Henry Russel Award
    - 1991
      - David J. Srolovitz (Box 1)
    - 1992
      - James M. Wilson (Box 1)
    - 1993
      - John C. Mitani (Box 1)
      - Jessy W. Grizzle (Box 1)
    - 1997, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1998, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1999, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Lectures
  The Lectures series includes paper copies and sound recordings of some of the past recipients of the Henry Russel Lectureship. The lectures are arranged alphabetically by award recipient.
  - Papers
    - Richard D. Alexander How Did Humans Evolve? Reflections on the Uniquely Unique Species (background material), 1989 (Box 2)
    - Francis A. Allen The Law as a Path to the World, 1979 (Box 2)
    - John Arthos Shakespeare and the Ancient World, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Arthur W. Burks Computers and Control in Society, 1979 included in Robots and Free Minds, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Halvor N. Christensen Membrane Domination of Biological Energy Exchanges: A Message of the 1978 Nobel Award in Chemistry, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Philip E. Converse Perspectives on the Democratic Process, 1987 (Box 2)
    - William Fulton Do We Understand Geometry of the Nineteenth Century?, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Leslie Kish Chance, Statistics, Sampling, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Abigail J. Stewart Uses of the Past: Toward a Psychology of Generations, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Maris A. Vinovskis Federal Compensatory Education Policies from Ronald Reagan to George W. Bush, 2004 (Box 2)
    - William Hoyt Worrell An Account of the Copts from Coptic Sources, 1942 (Box 2)
      (Introduction by Alfred H. White only)
  - Sound recordings
    The Audio Cassettes subseries contains recorded lectures given by six past recipients of the Henry Russel Lectureship. Three of the cassettes are dated 1975, 1984, 1991, and three cassettes are not dated.
    - Bernard Agranoff 1988, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - Leslie Bassett 1984, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - Minor J. Coon 1991, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - Thomas M. Donahue 1986, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - Sidney Fine 1985, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - George Kish 1975, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - Gérard A. Mouron 2002, audio cassette (Box 2)
    - Rowena Matthews 2003, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 2)
    - Maris Vinovskis 2004, 1 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - William Fulton 2005, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The series Photographs contains one folder of photographs portraying the plaque dedicated to all the recipients of the Henry Russel Lectureship, two photographs of Henry Russel which were reproduced from the biographical article written by Dr. Kraus, and one photograph of the December 1970 Henry Russel Lectureship awards dinner.
  - Photographs 1959, undated (Box 2)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series includes bulletins describing the Henry Russel Lecture and Award, flyers, programs, and scripts from the award ceremonies.
  - Bulletins 1962-1980 (Box 2)
  - Flyers 1987-2001 (Box 2)
  - Programs 1980-2004, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Scripts
    - Henry Russel Lecture 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - Henry Russel Lecture and Award Program 1997, 1999-2002 2004-, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Order of Exercises 1956, 1975-1985 (Box 2)
      (See also correspondence)